Guide to the George Yuzawa Papers TAM.442
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
George Yuzawa Papers
circa 1900-2009
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Yuzawa-Rubin, Patricia
Yuzawa, George
Yuzawa, Gene
TAM.442
7.5 Linear Feet in 7 record cartons and 7 folders.
The collection, spanning in date from 1908 to 2009, documents the life and work of Japanese American activist George Yuzawa through meeting minutes, reports, correspondence, notes, legal documents, press releases, newsletters, clippings, event flyers and programs, posters, buttons, video, audio, books, scrapbooks and photographs. The bulk of materials date from the 1940s—the time of his forced removal and incarceration at American concentration camps and his World War II military service—and from the 1970s through 1990s, during which he actively served in leadership positions in numerous Asian American organizations, including JAA, JACL, JAHFA, JAUC, and JANM. The oldest material in the collection is a subject file containing personal documents belonging to Nobuji Ashikaga (how or why Yuzawa acquired this is unknown). The most recent materials in the collection are contextual notes that daughter Patricia Yuzawa-Ruben sent to accompany the second accrual to the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The George Yuzawa Papers were donated by Gene Yuzawa and Patricia Yuzawa-Rubin in 2009. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2008.029, 2009.044, and 2011.049.
Arrangement
All series and subseries are arranged alphabetically by folder title and then chronologically.
The collection consists of 5 series:
The collection is arranged chronologically and by format, with Series I containing materials dating through World War II and Series II continuing with materials dated post-war. Oversize, print, ephemera, graphic, audiovisual and photographic materials have been separated and placed in Series III, IV and V. Folders within each series and subseries are arranged alphabetically by title and then chronologically.
The series and subseries arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I. Early Life through World War II, 1908-2004
Series II. Post World War II, 1938-2009
Subseries A: Redress Campaign and Remembrance, and Japanese American Military Service Memorials
Sub-subseries AI: Redress Campaign and World War II Remembrance
Sub-subseries AII: Japanese American Military Service Memorials
Subseries B: Japanese American National Museum (JANM)
Subseries C: Asian American Media Monitoring
Subseries D: Japanese American Association of New York (JAA)
Subseries E: Japanese American Help for the Aging (JAHFA)
Subseries F: Japanese American United Church (JAUC)
Subseries G: Personal Documents, Correspondence, and Subject Files
Series III. Oversize, Ephemera and Printed Materials, 1942-1999
Series IV. Video and Audio, undated
Series V. Photographs and Artwork, circa 1900-2008
Biographical Note
George Katsumi Yuzawa (1915-2011) was born in Los Angeles, California on February 21, 1915. George's Issei (first-generation immigrant) parents, Tamasaburo "James" and Bun "Mary" Yuzawa, emigrated to the United States from Nagano, Japan. In 1917, James Yuzawa established the Vermont Flower Shop located in downtown Los Angeles. He served a term as president of the Southern California Floral Association.
As a young man, George was a founding member of Boy Scout Troop 64 in Los Angeles and achieved the rank of Life Scout. In 1932, he and other young Nisei (second-generation Japanese Americans) helped Mas Satow, of the YMCA, establish the Japanese Athletic Union (JAU) to coordinate Nisei high school baseball, basketball, football, and track competitions in southern California. Yuzawa served as president of the JAU from 1935-1938. In 1933, George graduated from Manual Arts High School and attended Los Angeles City College, where he earned an associate's degree in Business. Discrimination against persons of Japanese ancestry limited job opportunities, even for educated Nisei. The prevailing employment climate led George to work with his father.
In 1940, George married Kimiko Hattori. She was the 23-year-old Nisei daughter of Tora and Seikichi "Walter" Hattori. Walter was the proprietor of Nippon Produce Market in Los Angeles. He was also an official in a local southern California produce union.
After the attack on Pearl Harbor, President Roosevelt signed Executive Order 9066 on February 19, 1942. The law forcibly removed all Japanese and Japanese Americans on the west coast to concentration camps under the direction of the Wartime Civilian Control Agency (WCCA). The Yuzawa and Hattori families were forcibly removed from their homes, and thereby made to abandon their prosperous businesses and dispose of whatever property they could not carry with them. They were among the 120,000 Americans of Japanese ancestry who were sent to ten concentration camps in the western and south central United States.
The Yuzawas and Hattoris, along with approximately 20,000 other Japanese Americans, endured several months at the Santa Anita racetrack, a temporary detention facility converted from stables. George served as the assistant director of men's athletics at Santa Anita. In September 1942, they were transported under armed guard to the Granada Relocation Center, also known as Camp Amache, in the desolate southeastern region of Colorado, near the small town of Granada. The Granada Relocation Center housed over 7,000 persons of Japanese ancestry, the majority of whom were American citizens or longtime permanent U.S. residents who were ineligible for citizenship under American immigration laws. Barbed wire fences surrounded the concentration camp and armed U.S. Army soldiers monitored the prisoners from guard towers. At Granada, George's father served as a block manager and George worked as the purchasing officer for the school system within the concentration camp.
George's younger sister, Chieko "Patricia," 19 years old at the time of the forced removal, was not permitted to join her family at Santa Anita or Granada after contracting tuberculosis. The U.S. government moved her to Hillcrest Sanitarium, located in the mountains of northwest Los Angeles. She died there in 1942, never seeing her parents again. During her stay, George was given permission to leave the camp (with an army escort) only once to visit her. The second and final time he went was to claim her body.
Prisoners were allowed to leave the camps if they had someone to sponsor them. In September 1943, the Wartime Relocation Authority (WRA) released George from the Granada Relocation Center because he had the promise of employment from the Annenberg and Erickson Florist Shop in New York City. Once in New York, he arranged for his wife and their parents to join him. In 1944, shortly after the family was reunited, George volunteered for the U.S. Army. He did this despite the fact that he was 29 years old, no longer subject to the military draft and not required to serve. He completed his basic training at Fort McClellan in Alabama and was then attached to an Army Intelligence unit. George was stationed in Tokyo as part of the American Occupation of Japan, where he served as a special officer for entertainment for enlisted U.S. military servicemen. He received an honorable discharge in 1946 and returned to New York City.
George attended City College of New York from 1946 to 1947 on the G.I. Bill, earning a certificate in foreign trade. After forming and operating a modest import-export business named HATCO Trading Company, Inc., George put aside his career ambitions in commercial trading to assist in his father's floral business.
In addition to the floral business, George made the time to volunteer for social, religious, political, and other charitable work. A devout Methodist, Yuzawa was a longtime chair and member of the Japanese American United Church.In the early 1970s, he worked with other Nisei and Sansei (third-generation Japanese American) civil rights activists to combat racial discrimination against Asians. These activists included future academic historian and author Mitziko Sawada, Kazu Iijima and Minn Matsuda, the founders of Asian Americans for Action, human rights activist Yuri ("Mary") Kochiyama, future AIDS advocate Suki Terada Ports, Princeton University theoretical physicist Michio Kaku, and Aiko Herzig-Yoshinaga, the individual who later discovered "the smoking gun" that demonstrated the Roosevelt Administration knew, back in 1942, that there was no military necessity for the Japanese American forced removal and incarceration.
This same core group of Nisei activists banded together to confront Paris clothing designer, Kenzo Takada. Kenzo, a Japanese national, owned several worldwide boutiques and used historically derogatory terminology for his trademarks and stores. The New York chapter board of the Japanese American Citizens' League (JACL) contacted New York Nisei attorney Moonray Kojima, who filed a lawsuit against Kenzo's Paris firm as well as its American distributor Mallory Outerwear. George and this same group protested the ILGWU's (International Ladies Garment Workers Union) implied anti-Japanese racism in its "Buy American" campaign. The Kenzo and ILGWU incidents prompted George and others to organize Asian Americans for Fair Media, Inc. (AAFM) in 1973. This group of Nisei volunteers monitored the local and national broadcast and print media for negative Asian stereotypes and racial slurs. In 1973, the AAFM published a booklet entitled Stereotypes and Realities: The Asian Image in the United States. In 1974, in recognition of George's work, the Eastern Regional Office of the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights asked him to serve as a consultant.
George also devoted much of his time between 1965 and the early 2000s attending to the needs of senior citizens. In 1965, he organized the Ad Hoc Committee of Concerned Asians in New York City to develop a strategy for addressing the housing needs of Issei and Nisei senior citizens. Japanese American Help for the Aging, Inc. (JAHFA) was formed in 1974. JAHFA was a grassroots, non-profit effort to help elderly Issei and Nisei in New York with various concerns such as bilingual assistance, access to medical care, information and referral, food delivery for shut-ins, group activities such as luncheons and field trips, and housing. JAHFA located senior residential housing at the Methodist Home in Riverdale and began placing Issei and Nisei seniors there in 1974. In the early 1980s, JAHFA became a standing committee of the Japanese American Association of New York (JAA) to secure additional financial and manpower resources.
In 1981, George served as a member of the East Coast Japanese Americans for Redress organization that advised the federal Commission on Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians and helped organize the November 1981 commission hearings in New York City. The hearings in turn helped shape the 1988 Civil Liberties Act in which President Ronald Reagan and the U.S. Congress apologized for the forced removal and incarceration of Japanese American citizens and permanent residents during WWII, authorized the payment of $20,000 to each victim who was still alive, and allocated $50 million for a public education fund.
As a vice president, board member, and committee chair of the Japanese American Association of New York (JAA), George organized various Japanese cultural, educational, and preservation activities in New York City.
George was a charter member of the Japanese American Lions Club of New York, a member and president of the Nisei Investors of New York, and a Day of Remembrance Committee member. He worked with the Japanese American National Museum (JANM) in Los Angeles to develop an Ellis Island exhibit titled "America's Concentration Camps." He was also a founding member (1987) of Asian & Pacific Islander Coalition on HIV/AIDS (APICHA), a member of the National Parks Conservation Association, and an advisor to Harmonia Opera.
Scope and Content Note
George Katsumi Yuzawa (1915–2011) was a Japanese-American community activist. He was involved in numerous social and political causes fighting racial discrimination against Asians and Asian Americans, providing aid for senior citizens, and organizing Japanese cultural events around New York City. The collection, spanning in date from 1908 to 2009, documents the life and work of Japanese American activist George Yuzawa through meeting minutes, reports, correspondence, notes, legal documents, press releases, newsletters, clippings, event flyers and programs, posters, buttons, video, audio, books, scrapbooks and photographs. The bulk of materials date from the 1940s—the time of his forced removal and incarceration at American concentration camps and his World War II military service—and from the 1970s through 1990s, during which he actively served in leadership positions in numerous Asian American organizations, including JAA, JACL, JAHFA, JAUC, and JANM. The oldest material in the collection is a subject file containing personal documents belonging to Nobuji Ashikaga (how or why Yuzawa acquired this is unknown). The most recent materials in the collection are contextual notes that daughter Patricia Yuzawa-Ruben sent to accompany the second accrual to the collection.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Military Intelligence Service Language School (Fort Snelling, Minn.); Amache (Colo.); Japanese Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History.; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States.; War Relocation Authority (United States); Photographs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Japanese Americans -- History -- 20th century.; Military records.; Newsletters.; Press releases.; Japanese Americans -- Civil rights; Manuscripts; Printed ephemera.; Minutes (administrative records); Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; Japanese American veterans; Programs (documents); Japanese Americans -- Reparations.; Yuzawa, Kimiko; Kojima, Moonray; Yoshinaga-Herzig, Aiko; Japanese American Association of New York; Amache Consumer Enterprises, Inc.; Rademaker, John Adrian, 1905-; Lindley, James G.; Japanese American National Museum (Los Angeles, Calif.); Japanese American Citizens' League; Yuzawa-Rubin, Patricia; Asian Americans for Fair Media; Japanese American Help for the Aging, Inc.; Myer, Dillon S. (Dillon Seymour), 1891-1982; YMCA of Los Angeles; Japanese American Athletic Union; Yuzawa, Chieko Patricia; Japanese American United Church; Yuzawa, Bun; West Side Federation for Senior Housing; Sasaki, Shōsuke, 1941-; Japanese American Social Services, Inc.; Isabella Geriatric Center; Butterick Fashion Marketing Co.; Mink, Patsy T., 1927-2002; Takada, Kenzo; Inouye, Daniel K., 1924-2012; Matsunaga, Spark M., 1916-1990; Herzig, Jack; Yuzawa, James T.; National Council for Japanese American Redress (NCJAR); Yuzawa, Gene; Brooklyn Botanic Garden; Cypress Hills Cemetery (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Woodlawn Cemetery (New York, N.Y.); Santa Anita Assembly Center (Calif.); Granada Relocation Center
- Series I: Early Life through World War II, 1908-2004
  Scope and Content Note
  Series consists largely of official documents, correspondence and clippings chronicling the experience of the Yuzawa and Hattori families at Granada Relocation Center in Granada, Colorado. During his time there, James T. Yuzawa held leadership roles, including representing fellow residents of Block 8K as block manager and serving as a board member of Amache Consumer Enterprises, Inc., a co-op established to serve residents within the camp. In these capacities, James was able to amass administrative documents documenting camp governance such as by-laws, financial reports, communications and directives from authorities, forms requesting and granting permission, letters of reference and lists of residents, relatives, and addresses as well as more personal items such as notebooks. These, along with documents that George Yuzawa preserved relating to arriving at, living in and leaving the camp, provide rich detail of the interaction between incarcerated Japanese American families and the War Relocation Authority. Also contained within this series are records George requested relating to his service in the U.S. Army during WWII and a few files on his life in Los Angeles, CA before incarceration. These include correspondence, programs, and forms documenting his involvement in the YMCA, Japanese American Athletic Union, and Boy Scouts of America.
  - Addresses of Prisoners at Concentration Camps in Livingston, Louisiana and Lordsburg, New Mexico Separated from Family in Amache, Colorado, Feb 10, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Amache Consumer Enterprises, Inc.: Analysis Report of Books and Records, Aug 31, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Amache Consumer Enterprises, Inc.: Audit Report of Books and Records, Feb 28, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Amache Consumer Enterprises, Inc.: Balance Sheet, Apr 29, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Amache Consumer Enterprises, Inc.: By-Laws, [1942-1944] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Amache Consumer Enterprises, Inc.: Certificate to James T. Yuzawa for Service on Board of Directors, Oct 26, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Amache Consumer Enterprises, Inc.: Consumer Cooperatives Information Booklets (in English and Japanese), 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Amache Consumer Enterprises, Inc.: Correspondence: M. Naruse (President) to James T. Yuzawa, Aug 2, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Amache Consumer Enterprises, Inc.: Flyer Advertisements, May 25-27, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Amache Consumer Enterprises, Inc.: List of Board of Directors, Committee Members, and Employees, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ashikaga, Nobuji: Passport Translation, Alien Seaman's ID Card, Reference Letters, 1908-1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Booklet of Collected Newspaper Articles on Pacific Front of World War II and Japanese Americans, [1941-1942] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Boy Scouts of America: Excerpts from Constitution and Application Form, [1940s] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Church of All Nations: Athletic Activities Leaflet, Sep 22, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Citizens National Bank of Los Angeles: Correspondence: H.B. Dickie to James T. Yuzawa (re: Chieko Yuzawa's accounts), May 17, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Civilian Exclusion Order No. 5, Apr 1, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Clipping from New York Times Magazine: "What We Don't Know is Likely to Hurt Us", May 14, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Disciples of Christ, Committee on War Services: Blank Data Forms (with accompanying letter), [1940s] (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Executive Order No. 9066, Feb 19, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - FBI: Correspondence: E.E. Conroy to George Yuzawa (re: inquiry into employment of JAs in defense industries), Oct 7, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: Amache Senior High School Yearbook, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: Camp Directory, [1940s] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: Charter for Community Government, [1940s] (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: Community Analysis Report, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: Correspondence: James G. Lindley (Project Director) to Community Council, Jan 12, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: Correspondence: James G. Lindley to James T. Yuzawa, Feb 11, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: Correspondence: James T. Yuzawa to Ray Gibbons (Council for Social Action), Apr 14, 1944-May 22, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: Correspondence: Samuel J. Gordon (Director of Adult Ed) to Bun Yuzawa, Feb 29, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: Directory of Staff and Internees, Jan 1943 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: Forum Discussion Series re: Leaving Concentration Camp: Lecture Schedule, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: James T. Yuzawa's Block Manager Files, [1942-1944] (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: John Adrian Rademaker (Community Analyst) Farewell Speech to Internees, Jun 3, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: List of Instructors and Students in Japanese Arts and Music Classes (handwritten), [1940s] (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: List of Interned Families by Block Residence, [1940s] (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: List of Persons Above 16 Years of Age in Block 8K, [1940s] (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: Names and Addresses of Internees and Their Relatives and Friends in Japan, [1940s] (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: "The Need for Community Leadership" (typescript), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: Petition for Permission for Internees to Reunite with Families, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Hillcrest Sanitarium at La Crescenta, California: Correspondence: Louis Boonshaft to James T. Yuzawa (re: Chieko Yuzawa), Sep 11, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Japanese American Athletic Union Souvenir Program, Mar 29-31, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - National Japanese American Student Relocation Council: Newsletter, Apr 20, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Resettlement Council of Japanese American Organizations in New York City, Sep 13, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Santa Anita Assembly Center: Directive to Evacuate to Granada Issued to George and Kimi Yuzawa, Sep 21, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Santa Anita Assembly Center: Schedule of Athletic Events, [1941] (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Seabrook Farms, Deerfield Packing Corporation: Instructions to All Employees re: Treatment of German Prisoners of War Contracted to Work at Company, Jun 17, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Sherwin Cody School of English: Brochure and Enrollment Form, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - University of California at Los Angeles Commencement Program, Jun 14, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - U.S. Army Service: Correspondence: George Yuzawa to James T. and Bun Yuzawa, Aug 6, 1944-Dec 13, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - U.S. Army Service: Discharge Papers (George Yuzawa), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - U.S. Army Service: Family Allowance of World War II Servicemen, [1940s] (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - U.S. Army Service: Military Intelligence Service Language School (MISLS) Commencement Program, Sep 23, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - U.S. Army Service: Special Orders (George Yuzawa), 1944-1947 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - U.S. Army Service: Veteran Benefits (forms and information), 1997-2004 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - U.S. Department of State: Memorandum re: Reunion of Internees with Their Families, Feb 7, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - War Relocation Authority: Application for Leave Assistance Grant and Travel Authorization (made by James T. Yuzawa), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - War Relocation Authority: "Civilian Living in Wartime" (booklet prepared for residents leaving camp), Feb 1944 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - War Relocation Authority: Correspondence: Dillon S. Myer (Director) to James G. Lindley, Nov 12, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 57)